A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller, Vice Presidential records, Working Papers of the Vice President, Series 18 FA384
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller vice presidential records, Working Papers of the Vice President, Series 18
1974-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
United States. Office of the Vice President
FA384
28 Cubic Feet 63 bound volumes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical/Historical note
President Gerald R. Ford nominated Nelson A. Rockefeller to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon in August 1974. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 26 18
Scope and Contents note
Over the course of Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as Vice President of the United States, he served on several commissions, including the National Commission on Water Quality. Vice President Rockefeller also served as chair of the Domestic Council. The majority of Rockefeller's actions as Vice President are documented in this series of 63 volumes. They contain schedules, agenda and minutes of meetings, position papers, and memoranda and correspondence generated as part of the Vice President's daily activities.
Volumes 9 through 20 focus on Rockefeller's involvement with President Ford's Domestic Council, while documentation of the Vice President's meeings with President Ford are in Volumes 27 through 31. Volumes 50 through 60 contain press materials issued by the VP's office and transcripts of Rockefeller's speeches, television appearances, press conferences, as well as statements and press releases issued by his office. Of particular note in Volume 32 is documentation of the fiscal crisis that affected New York City and State. The majority of the information was provided by T. Norman Hurd, Special Assistant to Vice President Rockefeller. While Rockefeller was Governor of New York, Hurd served successively as Budget Director, Director of State Operations, and Secretary to the Governor.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Richard Allison (FA377)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Central Files (FA378)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, National Commission on Water Quality (FA379)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, New York Office (FA380)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Joseph E. Persico (FA381)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Press Releases (FA382)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Speeches (FA383)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Foreign Affairs and National Security (FA385)
Arrangement
Alphabetically.
Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1976; Prevention and health; Public health; International relations -- United States; National security -- United States; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Public policy; Social policy; Social problems; Social sciences; Environmental sciences; Environmental policy; Energy; Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Drug control; Veterans -- United States; United States; Technology; International relations; International economic relations; Human rights; Government policy; Federal government -- United States; Water -- Pollution; Water -- Purification; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Water conservation
- Archives and Records (I) (Box 1, Volume 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Information on the disposition of the Vice President's papers at the conclusion of his tenure and plans for relocation to archival locations. Advance Plans. Central Files - Summary (correspondence). Central Files - Notes. Central Files - Name File (sender/addressee). Central Files - Subject File. Howe Files (Classified Files). Kightliner (photographer) Mrs. Rockefeller. Pagnotta, Frank R. (Personnel). Pagnotta, Frank R. (VP Personal). Pagnotta, Frank R. (Other - VP Administrative). Pagnotta, Frank R. (Gift) (tab only). Speeches (to 1974). Speeches (1975+). Press Releases. Secretariat/Allison. Allison/Notebooks. Allison/File Folders. Secretariat/Briefing Notes. Secretariat/Herter, Huldrum, Towell. Spoff. Wallison, Peter. Water Quality.
- Archives and Records (II - Central Files Manual) (Box 2, Volume 2)
  Instructions on how to categorize, file, and dispose of correspondence. Filing categories and manual (A-Z) Index to Subjects (A-Z)
- Briefing Papers for the Vice President, 1975 February-July (Box 3, Volume 3)
  Includes schedules of meetings; talking points; biographical information on people NAR would be meeting; fact sheets; agendas; correspondence and reports. February 1975; March 1975; July 1975
- Briefing Papers for the Vice President, 1975 August-September 29 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  Includes schedules of meetings; talking points; biographical information on people NAR would be meeting; fact sheets; agendas; correspondence and reports. August 1975; September 1-29, 1975
- Briefing Papers for the Vice President, 1975 September 29-December 31 (Box 5, Volume 5)
  Includes schedules of meetings; talking points; biographical information on people NAR would be meeting; fact sheets; agendas; correspondence and reports. September 29-30, 1975; October 1975; November 1975; December 1975
- Briefing Papers for the Vice President, 1976 January-March (Box 6, Volume 6)
  Includes schedules of meetings; talking points; biographical information on people NAR would be meeting; fact sheets; agendas; correspondence and reports. January 1976; February 1976; March 1976
- Briefing Papers for the Vice President, 1976 April 1976-1977 January (Box 7, Volume 7)
  Includes schedules of meetings; talking points; biographical information on people NAR would be meeting; fact sheets; agendas; correspondence and reports. April 1976; May 1976; June 1976; July 1976; August 1976; September 1976; October 1976; November 1976; December 1976; January 1977
- Digests Prepared by Jeff Krolik, 1975 July-1976 August (Box 8, Volume 8)
  Summaries of speeches, papers, and reports on various issues.
- Domestic Council, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Volume 9)
  Domestic Council - General. Background Papers to February 13, 1975 -- summary of council, membership, purpose. Presidential Assignment, February 13, 1975. Review of National Domestic Needs - March 20, 1975 (tab only). Preparation for Domestic Council Meeting (March-June 1975). Drug Review Task Force (April-September 1975) -- memoranda, correspondence, reports. U.S. Environmental Policy (April 1975) -- memoranda, correspondence, reports. Intergovernmental Relations Proposal (August 1975-January 1976) -- memoranda, correspondence, reports. Summer Jobs for Urban Youth (Summer 1975) -- memoranda, correspondence, reports. June 11, 1975 - December 15, 1975 -- meeting agendas, minutes, organizational chart. Domestic Council Meeting (June 10, 1975) -- memoranda, minutes.
- Domestic Council Activities Inventory, 1975 March 7 (Box 10, Volume 10)
  Issues being addressed; on whose orders, participants, and due dates for project. Intermediate Domestic Council Activities: Statistical Summary Natural Resources Human Resources Community Development General Government Intergovernmental Relations Director's Office Staff Secretary
  Mid- and Long-Range Domestic Council Activities: Statistical Summary Natural Resources Human Resources Community Development general Government Intergovernmental Relations
  Summary of Domestic Council: Natural Resources Human Resources Community Development Domestic Council Committees
- Domestic Council Study of National Domestic Needs and Major Policy Problems: Initial Assessments by Departments (Submitted to the President March 20, 1975), 1975 March 20 (Box 11, Volume 11)
  Identification of issues to be addressed by the Domestic Council. Background Documents. Action. Agriculture Department. Commerce Department. Council of Economic Advisors. Council on Environmental Quality. Economic Policy Board. Energy Resources Council. Environmental Protection Agency. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Department of Housing and Urban Development. Department of the Interior. Department of Justice. Department of Labor. Department of Transportation. Department of the Treasury. Veterans Administration
- Domestic Council, 1975 (Box 12, Volume 12)
  Issues of "Welfare, An 'Income Supplement Program,'" and National Health Insurance. Federal Social Programs Study (March - July 1975). Presidential Approval (May 15, 1975). May 16 - June 30, 1975. July 1-23, 1975. Domestic Policy Review (July - August 1975). Presidential Approval (July 24, 1975). July 25 - August 30, 1975.
- Domestic Council, 1975-1976 (Box 13, Volume 13)
  Plans to hold Public Forums on Domestic Policy Domestic Council, Domestic Policy Review and Public Forums Policy (September 1975 - February 1976). Presidential Approval (September 10, 1975). Cabinet Meeting (September 17, 1975). Memo to the Domestic Council (September 17, 1976). October 1 - November 5, 1975. Presidential Approval (November 6, 1975). November 7 - December 14, 1975. Report to the President (December 15/17, 1975). Distribution and Thank-You notes (December 1975 - February 1976).
- Domestic Council, 1975 (Box 14, Volume 14)
  Public Forums on Domestic Policy (September - December 1975) - Media Activity -- clippings, press kits, press releases from forums
- Domestic Council Public Forums - Thank-You Letters, 1975 (Box 15, Volume 15)
  Copies of letters from NAR to those who assisted and participated in forums. October 21, 1975 - Denver, Colorado. October 28, 1975 - Tampa, Florida. November 11, 1975 - Austin, Texas. December 8-9, 1975 - Los Angeles, California.
- Domestic Council Public Forums - Thank-You Letters, 1975 (Box 16, Volume 16)
  Copies of letters from NAR to those who assisted and participated in forums. November 18, 1975 - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. November 25, 1975 -- Indianapolis, Indiana. Staff.
- Domestic Council Privacy Committee (I), 1975 January-October (Box 17, Volume 17)
  Committee on Right to Privacy for all Americans. January - April 1975. May - June 1975. July - October 1975.
- Domestic Council Privacy Committee (II), 1975 November- 1976 April (Box 18, Volume 18)
  Correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes.
- Domestic Council Privacy Committee (III), 1976 May-1977 January (Box 19, Volume 19)
- Domestic Council Privacy Committee, 1976 (Box 20, Volume 20)
  Memo on Transfer of Privacy Committee Functions and Staff Report on "National Information Policy" (September 14, 1976): Executive Summary. Table of Contents. Chapter One - statement of the problem. Chapter Two - major information policy issues. Issue Cluster I - Government Information Collection, Transformation, Dissemination. Issue Cluster II - Information on Commerce, a Resource for Publication. Issue Cluster III - The Interaction between Technology and Government. Issue Cluster IV - International Implications of Information Policies and Development. Issue Cluster V - Preparation for the Information Summary. Chapter Three -- Recommendation.
- Energy Independence Authority, 1975 January-August (Box 21, Volume 21)
  Establishment of organization to help the United States become independent of foreign sources of energy and to assist in the formulation of a national energy policy: January - February 1975. March 1975 April 1975. May 1975. Presidential Approval (May 2, 1975). May 3-9, 1975. Business Council Meeting, Hot Springs, VA (May 9, 1975). May 10-21, 1975. Presidential Approval (May 22, 1975). Domestic Council Review Group Meeting (May 23, 1975). May 22-31, 1975. June 1975. July 1975. Presidential Option Papers (August 6-26, 1975). August 25-31, 1975. Presidential Option Memo (August 30, 1975).
- Energy Independence Authority, 1975 September-December (Box 22, Volume 22)
  September 1975. Presidential Option Memo (September 15, 1975). September 17-30, 1975. October 1975 Business Executives' Meeting (October 6, 1975). October 9, 1975 Briefing Book: Fact Sheet, Questions and Answers, EIA Legislation. October 10, 1975: Fact Sheet and Legislation. October 9-31, 1975. November 1975. U.S. Chamber of Commerce (November 6, 1975). November 7-30, 1975. December 1975. National Association of Manufacturers Speech (December 5, 1975). December 6-31, 1975.
- Energy Independence Authority, 1976 January-March (Box 23, Volume 23)
  January 1976: Farmer Cooperatives (January 14, 1976). January 15-20, 1976. Bi-Partisan Congressional Breakfast (January 21, 1976). January 22-31.
  February 1976: Atomic Industrial Forum (February 10, 1976). AFL-CIO, Miami (February 11-12, 1976): Brief Summary of EIA. EIA Fact Sheet. Senate Bill S.2532. Congressional Committees with EIA Referrals. Energy Material From Budget. Federal Energy Administration (FEA) Study on Capital Needs. FEA Capital Requirements Memorandum (February 10, 1976). Charts from Energy Facts II. Congressman Mike McCormack [Washington] Statistical Data with Charts. Nuclear Power Facts. U.S. Domestic Energy Forecasts Through 1985. President's Remarks on EIA at AFL-CIO Convention. Banker's Trust Report on Capital Requirements (tab only). [U.S. Sen. Jacob] Javits [R-NY] Letter on National Technology Development Corporation Bill. Summary of Ford Foundation Report: "Financing the Energy Industry." Capital Demands Summary from Ford Foundation Report. Energy Resource Development Administration (ERDA) Charts. February 13-24, 1976: "The New York Times" Op-Ed Article (February 24, 1976), written by Nelson Rockefeller. February 24-29, 1976.
  March 1976: Executive Summary Overview National Industrial Forum (March 10, 1976). Senate Lunches (March 10 an:d 16, 1976). Links Club (March 15, 1976) - meeting with leaders of New York City Financial Community. Business Roundtable Dinner (March 17, 1976). Senate Banking Lunch (March 18, 1976). March 10-31, 1976.
- Energy Independence Authority, 1976 April-1977 January (Box 24, Volume 24)
  April 1976: EIA Lunch (April 7, 1976). EIA Dinner (April 7, 1976). Senate Lunch (April 8, 1976). Senate Testimony (April 12, 1976): Prepared Statement for Vice President Rockefeller. Prepared Statement for Frank G. Zarb, Administrator, FEA. Need for EIA. EIA Portfolio Alternatives. EIA Investment Activities by Sector. Scope of EIA Investment Activity. Budgetary Treatment of EIA. Employment Induced by EIA Activity. Economic Impact of EIA. Qs and As (tab only). EIA Fact Sheet. April 12-18, 1976. Congressional Lunch (April 29, 1976). April 29-30, 1976.
  May 1976. June 1976: "Wall Street Journal" lunch (June 7, 1976). June 8-30, 1976. July 1976-January 1977.
- Executive Office of Intergovernmental Coordination Proposal, 1976 January 8 (Box 25, Volume 25)
  Plan for government office to coordinate actions between the federal government and state and local governments.
- General Revenue Sharing, 1975-1976 (Box 26, Volume 26)
  Memoranda and correspondence for full administration support of plan: 1975. February 4-29, 1976. March 1976. April 1976. May 1976. June 1976. July 1976. August 1976. September 1976. October 1976.
- Meetings with the President, 1974 December 27-1975 September 10 (Box 27, Volume 27)
  Includes agendas, schedules, and minutes of meetings; correspondence, memoranda and reports: December 27, 1974. March 20, 1975. May 2, 1975. May 8, 1975. May 15, 1975. May 22, 1975. June 6, 1975. June 12, 1975. June 19, 1975. June 24, 1975. July 10, 1975. July 16, 1975. July 24, 1975. August 6, 1975. August 26, 1975. September 3, 1975. September 10, 1975.
- Meetings with the President, 1975 September 16-December (Box 28, Volume 28)
  Includes agendas, schedules, and minutes of meetings; correspondence, memoranda and reports: September 16, 1975. September 25, 1975. October 2, 1975. October 8, 1975. October 15, 1975. October 22, 1975. October 28, 1975. November 10, 1975. November 19, 1975. December 10, 1975. December 16, 1975.
- Meetings with the President, 1976 January-May (Box 29, Volume 29)
  Includes agendas, schedules, and minutes of meetings; correspondence, memoranda and reports: January 8, 1976. January 14, 1976. January 15, 1976. January 21, 1976. January 27, 1976. February 5, 1976. February 11, 1976. February 19, 1976 (two meetings). March 4, 1976. March 11, 1976. March 18, 1976. April 7, 1976. April 12, 1976. April 22, 1976. May 1, 1976. May 11, 1976. May 17, 1976. May 18, 1976. May 19, 1976. May 20, 1976. May 27, 1976.
- Meetings with the President, 1976 June-August (Box 30, Volume 30)
  Includes agendas, schedules, and minutes of meetings; correspondence, memoranda and reports: June 1, 1976. June 4, 1976. June 10, 1976. June 16, 1976. June 24, 1976. July 1, 1976. July 8, 1976. July 15, 1976. July 22, 1976. July 27, 1976. July 29, 1976. August 3, 1976 August 12, 1976.
- Meetings with the President, 1976 September-1977 January (Box 31, Volume 31)
  Includes agendas, schedules, and minutes of meetings; correspondence, memoranda and reports: September 9, 1976. September 14, 1976. September 30, 1976. November 5, 1976. November 18, 1976. November 24, 1976. December 2, 1976. December 8, 1976. December 15, 1976. January 5, 1977. January 13, 1977.
- New York City, 1975-1976 (Box 32, Volume 32)
  Information on the fiscal crisis in New York State and New York City, reports primarily submitted by T. Norman Hurd: New York City Reports Index January - March April - May June - July August - September October - December Supplementary Material 1975 Supplementary Material 1976
- Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP), 1975-1976 (Box 33, Volume 33)
  Establishment of OSTP: January - June 1975. July - December 1975. January - August 1976. Selection of Director, OSTP: [Simon] Ramo [scientist and industrialist] Possibility (February - April 1976). [Guy] Stever [de jure advisor to OSTP] Nomination (April - August 1976).
- Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP), 1975 July-1976 August (Box 34, Volume 34)
  Science and Technology Advisory and Consulting Groups (Ramo - Baker Groups) - Organizational and General. Meeting of Scientific Leaders (July 17, 1975): Presidential Authorization of Agenda. Correspondence. Handouts. Minutes. Follow-Up (July - August 1975). Meeting of Scientific Leaders (September 4, 1975): Agenda. Correspondence. Handouts. Minutes. Follow-Up (September 1975). Presentation of National Medal of Science (September 18, 1975). Establishment of Science and Technology Advisory Groups (September-December 1975). Science Advisory Groups (January - August 1976).
- Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP), 1975 December-1976 August (Box 35, Volume 35)
  Science and Technology Advisory and Consulting Groups (Ramo - Baker Groups). Science Advisory Groups Meetings; December 1-2, 1975, Washington, DC. January 14-15, 1976, Washington, DC. March 11-12, 1976, Washington, DC. April 22-23, 1976, Moffett Field, California. June 17-18, 1976, Washington, DC. August 5-6, 1976, Los Angeles, California.
- Office of Science and Technology Policy (OSTP), 1976 September 1 (Box 36, Volume 36)
  Science and Technology Advisory and Consulting Groups (Ramo - Baker Groups) - Report, September 1, 1976
- Office of the Vice President - General - Book I, 1975-1977 (Box 37, Volume 37)
  Initial Presidential Assignments - list of assignments undertaken by NAR in the Ford Administration. Subsequent Presidential Assignments and Authorizations. White House Staff Meetings - minutes and agendas of Senior White House Staff Meetings.
- Office of the Vice President - General - Book II, 1975-1977 (Box 38, Volume 38)
  Capitol Hill Club: April - June 1975; July - December 1975; 1976. Miscellaneous. Transition - correspondence and memoranda concerning the change of administrations from President Ford to President Carter.
- Office of the Vice President - Descriptions and Procedures, Book I, 1976 November 18 (Box 39, Volume 39)
  Organizational chart, job descriptions of VP staff, procedural memoranda.
- Office of the Vice President - Descriptions and Procedures, Book II, 1976 November 18 (Box 40, Volume 40)
  Procedural memoranda of how the functions of the VP are undertaken.
- Productivity Commission, 1974 December-1975 July (Box 41, Volume 41)
  Materials on the National Commission on Productivity and Work Quality, which aimed to increase the productivity of the American economy and improve the morale and quality of work of the American worker. March-April 1975: General. Program Description of Activities. Presidential Request (March 17, 1975). Executive Committee Meeting (April 8, 1975). Commission Meeting (April 17, 1975). May-June 1975: General. Executive Committee Meeting (May 14, 1975). Executive Committee Meeting (June 18, 1975). Commission Meeting (June 24, 1975). July 1975: General. Executive Committee Meeting (July 25, 1975).
- Productivity Commission, 1975 August-December (Box 42, Volume 42)
  Materials on the National Commission on Productivity and Work Quality, which aimed to increase the productivity of the American economy and improve the morale and quality of work of the American worker. August-September 1975: General. Executive Committee Meeting (September 23, 1975). October-November 1975: General. Statement. European Association of National Productivity Center (EANPC). Conference (September 29-October 3), Washington, DC. Executive Committee Meeting (November 10, 1975). December 1975: General. Budget Proposal (December 9, 1975). Executive Committee Meeting (December 10, 1975). Report to the President and Congress (December 31, 1975).
- Productivity Center, 1976 January-1977 January (Box 43, Volume 43)
  January-February 1976: General. Executive Committee Meeting (January 13, 1976). March-April 1976. May-June 1976: General. Meeting (May 18, 1976). National Conference on Regulatory Reform (May 26, 1976), Washington, DC. July 1976-January 1977: General. Executive Committee Meeting (July 7, 1976). Human Resources Committee Meeting (July 28, 1976). Capital/Technology Committee Meeting (September 13, 1976). FY 78 Budget Request (October 12/27, 1978).
- National Commission on Water Quality (I), 1973-1976 (Box 44, Volume 44)
  Report to Congress (March 18, 1976). The Act establishing the NCWQ (October 18, 1972). Membership of Commission, 1973 original list, 1975 revised list. Biographies of Commissioners. Biographies of Staff. Study Plan by NAR (June 1973). Study Plan approved by Commission (February 1974). Study Design: Industry (June 1974). Study Design: Environmental (March 1975). National Academy of Sciences Study Commission on Water Quality Policy (February 1974). Institute for Ecology (T.I.E.) Advisory Committee (July 1974). Budget and Expenditures. Publications List. Repositories for Reports. Progress Report. NAR Archives Box List. NAR Archives Folder List. NAR Archives Alphabetical Subject List.
- National Commission on Water Quality (II), 1973-1976 (Box 45, Volume 45)
  Agendas, NCWQ Meetings. Minutes, NCWQ Meetings. Domestic Council Task Force Report, October 1975.
- Weekly Briefing Notes for the President and Vice President and STATUS: A Monthly Chartbook of Social and Economic Trends, 1975-1977 (Box 46, Volume 46)